Register of the Ziemeļkalifornijas latviešu biedrība records
Hoover Institution Archives
Ziemeļkalifornijas latviešu biedrība records
1951-2015
2016C8
Hoover Institution Archives
21 manuscript boxes (8.8 linear feet)
The Ziemeļkalifornijas latviešu biedrība (Northern California Latvian Association) records pertain to the largest organization in the Latvian community of Northern California and consist of minutes, correspondence, membership and financial records, bulletins, and printed matter relating to Latvian émigré affairs and Latvians in the United States. The records document the internal workings of the organization and its public activities, including the many cultural events sponsored by the association. There are also materials relating to efforts to keep the cause of Baltic independence alive during the Cold War, including protests over Soviet occupation of the Baltic States.
Ziemelkalifornijas latviešu biedrība.
Access
The collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2015.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Historical Note
Founded in 1958, the Ziemeļkalifornijas latviešu biedrība (Northern California Latvian Association) has served as a focal point in the community life of Latvians in Northern California. The association has sponsored cultural events and organized recreational activities for young people. It sought to preserve the cause of independence for the Baltic States during the Cold War, and after Baltic independence was renewed in 1991, the association promoted assistance to newly sovereign Latvia. The association publishes Ziemeļkalifornijas Apskats.
Scope and Content of Collection
The Ziemeļkalifornijas latviešu biedrība (Northern California Latvian Association) records pertain to the largest organization in the Latvian community of Northern California and consist of minutes, correspondence, membership and financial records, bulletins, and printed matter relating to Latvian émigré affairs and Latvians in the United States. The records document the internal workings of the organization and its public activities, including the many cultural events sponsored by the association. There are also materials relating to efforts to keep the cause of Baltic independence alive during the Cold War, including protests over Soviet occupation of the Baltic States.
The records include papers relating to two earlier organizations, the Latviešu Apvienībus Oaklandē and the Latviešu Kopa Los Gatosa. There are also extensive materials concerning the building of a proposed Latvian center in Orinda, California, a project that never came to fruition. The printed matter series includes many issues of Ziemeļkalifornijas Apskats, the association's monthly publication. There are also numerous issues of Zelta Vārtu Vēstis, the publication of the Latvian Evangelical Lutheran church. Additionally, the collection contains significant materials about youth activities organized by the association.
Latvia--Emigration and immigration.; Latvians--United States.
- Correspondence, 1965-2008
  - 1965-1969 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - 1970-1971 (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - 1972 (Box-folder 1: 3-4)
  - 1973 (Box-folder 1: 5-6)
  - 1974 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - 1975 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - 1976 (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - 1977 (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - 1978 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - 1979 (Box-folder 1: 12)
  - 1980 (Box-folder 1: 13)
  - 1981 (Box-folder 1: 14)
  - 1982 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - 1983 (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - 1984 (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - 1985-1989 (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - 1990-1995 (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - 1996-1999 (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - 2000-2003 (Box-folder 2: 7)
  - 2004-2008 (Box-folder 2: 8)
- Articles of Incorporation, 1958-1988 (Box-folder 2: 9)
- Rules and Procedures, 1956-2013 (Box-folder 2: 10)
- Statutes and By-laws, 1958-2014
  - 1958 (Box-folder 2: 11, Box-folder 3: 1)
  - 1970-2014 (Box-folder 3: 2)
- Minutes of Meetings, 1958-2014
  - Board of Directors (Executive Committee), 1959-2014
    - 1959 (Box-folder 3: 3)
    - 1960-1961 (Box-folder 3: 4)
    - 1962 (Box-folder 3: 5)
    - 1964-1965 (Box-folder 3: 6)
    - 1966 (Box-folder 3: 7)
    - 1967-1969 (Box-folder 3: 8)
    - 1970-1975 (Box-folder 3: 9)
    - 1976-1977 (Box-folder 3: 10)
    - 1978 (Box-folder 3: 11)
    - 1980-1981 (Box-folder 3: 12)
    - 1982-1983 (Box-folder 3: 13)
    - 1984-1985 (Box-folder 3: 14)
    - 1986-1987 (Box-folder 4: 1)
    - 1988 (Box-folder 4: 2)
    - 1989-1993 (Box-folder 4: 3)
    - 1993 (Box-folder 4: 4)
    - 1994 (Box-folder 4: 5)
    - 1995 (Box-folder 4: 6)
    - 1996 (Box-folder 4: 7)
    - 1997 (Box-folder 4: 8)
    - 1998 (Box-folder 4: 9)
    - 1999 (Box-folder 4: 10)
    - 2000 (Box-folder 4: 11)
    - 2001 (Box-folder 4: 12)
    - 2002 (Box-folder 4: 13)
    - 2003 (Box-folder 5: 1)
    - 2004 (Box-folder 5: 2)
    - 2005 (Box-folder 5: 3)
    - 2006 (Box-folder 5: 4)
    - 2007 (Box-folder 5: 5)
    - 2008 (Box-folder 5: 6)
    - 2009 (Box-folder 5: 7)
    - 2010 (Box-folder 5: 8)
    - 2011 (Box-folder 5: 9)
    - 2012 (Box-folder 5: 10)
    - 2013 (Box-folder 5: 11)
    - 2014 (Box-folder 5: 12)
  - Council, 1958-2014
    - 1958-1960 (Box-folder 5: 13)
    - 1965-1979 (Box-folder 5: 14)
    - 1984-1989 (Box-folder 6: 1)
    - 1990-1999 (Box-folder 6: 2)
    - 2000-2004 (Box-folder 6: 3)
    - 2005-2010 (Box-folder 6: 4)
    - 2011-2014 (Box-folder 6: 5)
  - General assembly of members, 1958-2014
    - 1958-1959 (Box-folder 6: 6)
    - 1960-1962 (Box-folder 6: 7)
    - 1963-1965 (Box-folder 6: 8)
    - 1966-1968 (Box-folder 6: 9)
    - 1970-1975 (Box-folder 6: 10)
    - 1976-1978 (Box-folder 6: 11)
    - 1980-1984 (Box-folder 6: 12)
    - 1985-1988 (Box-folder 6: 13)
    - 1993-1995 (Box-folder 6: 14)
    - 1996-1999 (Box-folder 6: 15)
    - 2000-2002 (Box-folder 6: 16)
    - 2003-2005 (Box-folder 6: 17)
    - 2006-2008 (Box-folder 6: 18)
    - 2009-2011 (Box-folder 6: 19)
    - 2012-2014 (Box-folder 7: 1)
- Activities File, 1958-2014
  Scope and Contents note
  Correspondence, announcements, flyers, and minutes of meetings.
  - Aivars Baumanis visit, 1994 (Box-folder 7: 2)
  - Choir, 1974-1979 (Box-folder 7: 3)
  - Cultural and social events, 1968-2014
    - General, 1968-2010 (Box-folder 7: 4-5)
    - Baltic Day and Baltic Night celebrations, 1991-1998 (Box-folder 7: 6)
    - Cantus concert, 1995 (Box-folder 7: 7)
    - Choir, 1974-1979 (Box-folder 7: 8)
    - Folk dance group, Ritenītis, 1966-1969 (Box-folder 7: 9)
    - Independence Day celebrations, 1985-2014 (Box-folder 7: 10-11)
    - Līča Vēji vocal ensemble, 1976-1984 (Box-folder 7: 12)
    - Rīga Dome Boys Choir concert, 2000 (Box-folder 7: 13)
    - Theater group, 1995 (Box-folder 7: 14)
  - Guntis Ulmanis visit, 1997 (Box-folder 8: 1)
  - Latvijas Atbalsta Grupa, 1997-1998 (Box-folder 8: 2)
  - Volleyball team, 1978 (Box-folder 8: 3)
  - Youth Council, 1958-1983
    - 1958-1969 (Box-folder 8: 4)
    - 1970-1977 (Box-folder 8: 5)
    - 1978-1980 (Box-folder 8: 6)
    - 1981-1983 (Box-folder 8: 7)
    - Photographs, 1981 (Box-folder 8: 8)
  - Ziemeļkalifornijas Apskats subscriber lists, 1969-2008 (Box-folder 8: 9)
- Accounts File, 1959-2009
  - Applications for tax-exempt status, 1959-1989 (Box-folder 8: 10, Box-folder 9: 1-3)
  - Balances, 1959-2009
    Includes itemized receipts and expenditures.
    - 1959-1968 (Box-folder 9: 4)
    - 1968-1969 (Box-folder 9: 5)
    - 1970-1971 (Box-folder 9: 6)
    - 1972-1974 (Box-folder 9: 7)
    - 1975-1979 (Box-folder 9: 8)
    - 1980-1982 (Box-folder 9: 9)
    - 1983-1987 (Box-folder 10: 1)
    - 1988-1989 (Box-folder 10: 2)
    - 1990-1991 (Box-folder 10: 3)
    - 1992-1997 (Box-folder 10: 4)
    - 1998-1999 (Box-folder 10: 5)
    - 2000-2001 (Box-folder 10: 6)
    - 2002-2003 (Box-folder 10: 7)
    - 2004 (Box-folder 10: 8)
    - 2005-2009 (Box-folder 10: 9)
- Membership Lists, 1989-2014
  - General, 1989-2014 (Box-folder 11: 1-2)
  - Board members, 2000-2007 (Box-folder 11: 3)
- List of Latvian Students Studying at U.C. Berkeley and U.C. San Francisco, 1957 (Box-folder 11: 4)
- Questionnaire, 1996 (Box-folder 11: 5)
- Aldis Simsons File, 1991-2011
  Includes correspondence, notes, and annotated minutes of meetings.
  - 1991-1992 (Box-folder 11: 6)
  - 1993-1994 (Box-folder 11: 7)
  - 1995-1996 (Box-folder 11: 8)
  - 1997 (Box-folder 11: 9)
  - 1998 (Box-folder 11: 10)
  - 1999 (Box-folder 11: 11)
  - 2000 (Box-folder 11: 12)
  - 2001-2003 (Box-folder 12: 1)
  - 2004-2005 (Box-folder 12: 2)
  - 2006-2007 (Box-folder 12: 3)
  - 2008-2011 (Box-folder 12: 4)
- Latviešu Apvienības Oaklandē File, 1951-1958
  - Constitution and statutes, 1951 (Box-folder 12: 5)
  - Minutes of meetings, 1951-1958 (Box-folder 12: 6)
  - Newsletter and correspondence, 1951-1958 (Box-folder 12: 7)
  - Commemorative album, 1956 (Box-folder 12: 8)
  - Inventory, 1951-1958 (Box-folder 12: 9)
- Latviešu Kopa Los Gatosa File, 1952-1953
  - American Latvian Association correspondence, 1952 (Box-folder 13: 1-3)
  - Articles, 1952 (Box-folder 13: 4)
  - Minutes of meetings, 1952-1953 (Box-folder 13: 5)
- American Latvian Association File, 1953-2010
  Includes bulletins, correspondence, and newsletters.
  - 1953 (Box-folder 13: 6)
  - 1954-1958 (Box-folder 13: 7)
  - 1961-1968 (Box-folder 13: 8)
  - 1969-1970 (Box-folder 13: 9)
  - 1971-1978 (Box-folder 13: 10)
  - 1982-1985 (Box-folder 13: 11)
  - 1986-1987 (Box-folder 13: 12)
  - 1988-1989 (Box-folder 14: 1)
  - 1990 (Box-folder 14: 2)
  - 1990-1991 (Box-folder 14: 3)
  - 1992-1993 (Box-folder 14: 4)
  - 1994-1995 (Box-folder 14: 5)
  - 1998-2000 (Box-folder 14: 6)
  - 2001-2006 (Box-folder 14: 7)
  - 2010 (Box-folder 14: 8)
- Subject File, 1973-1997
  - Baltic Alliance of Northern California, 1991-1997 (Box-folder 14: 9)
  - Latvian Foundation, Inc., 1973 (Box-folder 14: 10)
  - Proposed Orinda center project, 1986-1989 (Box-folder 14: 11-12)
  - Proposed Orinda center project, 1989-1992 (Box-folder 15: 1-6)
- CD-R, Latviešu Sanfrancisko un tās apkārtnē, 2004 (Box-folder 15: 7)
- Photographs, 1970-1991
  - Miscellaneous, 1970-1982 (Box-folder 15: 8)
  - 18 prints depicting protest at Soviet consulate in San Francisco, 1991 (Box-folder 15: 9)
- Printed Matter, 1959-2015
  - Clippings, 1990-2004 (Box-folder 15: 10-12)
  - Reports, 1991-2014
    - Rietumkrasta Latviešu Izglītības Centra 2012. gada pārskats (Box-folder 16: 1)
    - Gada Darbības Pārskats, Amerikas Latviešu Apvienība, 2012-2014 (Box-folder 16: 2)
    - Commission on Security and Cooperation in Europe, 1991 (Box-folder 16: 3)
  - Programs, 1992-1998 (Box-folder 16: 4)
  - Serial issues, 1959-2015
    - Bitīte, 1970 (Box-folder 16: 5)
    - Čikāgas Ziņas, 2011-2013 (Box-folder 16: 6)
    - Dienvidkalifornijas Latviešu Informācijas Biļetens, 1998-2012 (Box-folder 16: 7)
    - Gaŗezera Ziņas, 1974 (Box-folder 16: 8)
    - Latvian Dimensions, 2011-2013 (Box-folder 16: 9)
    - Latvietis Latvietim, 1974-1975 (Box-folder 16: 10)
    - Zelta Rīts, 1989 (Box-folder 16: 11)
    - Zelta Vārtu Vēstis
      - 1960 (Box-folder 16: 12)
      - 1961 (Box-folder 16: 13)
      - 1968-1969 (Box-folder 16: 14)
      - 1970 (Box-folder 17: 1)
      - 1971 (Box-folder 17: 2)
      - 1972 (Box-folder 17: 3-4)
      - 1973 (Box-folder 17: 5)
      - 2011-2012 (Box-folder 17: 6)
    - Ziemeļkalifornijas Apskats
      - 1964-1976 (Box-folder 17: 7)
      - 1977-1978 (Box-folder 18: 1)
      - 1979-1981 (Box-folder 18: 2)
      - 1982 (Box-folder 18: 3)
      - 1982-1985 (Box-folder 18: 4)
      - 1992-1997 (Box-folder 18: 5)
      - 1998 (Box-folder 18: 6)
      - 1999 (Box-folder 18: 7)
      - 2000 (Box-folder 18: 8)
      - 2001 (Box-folder 19: 1)
      - 2002 (Box-folder 19: 2)
      - 2003 (Box-folder 19: 3)
      - 2004 (Box-folder 19: 4)
      - 2005 (Box-folder 19: 5)
      - 2006-2007 (Box-folder 19: 6)
      - 2008 (Box-folder 19: 7-8)
      - 2009 (Box-folder 20: 1-2)
      - 2010 (Box-folder 20: 3-4)
      - 2011 (Box-folder 20: 5-6)
      - 2012 (Box-folder 21: 1)
      - 2013 (Box-folder 21: 2-3)
      - 2014 (Box-folder 21: 4)
      - 2014-2015 (Box-folder 21: 5)
    - Ziemeļkalifornijas Latviešu Biedrība Apkārtraksts, 1959 (Box-folder 21: 6)
    - Ziemeļkalifornijas Latviešu Ev.-Lut. draudzes
      - 1966-1969 (Box-folder 21: 7)
      - 1971-1972 (Box-folder 21: 8)
      - 1974-1975 (Box-folder 21: 9)
  - Telephone books, 1999-2014 (Box-folder 21: 10)